Guide to the Jesse Pyrant Andrews photographs, 1973-2012
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Jesse Pyrant Andrews photographs 1973-2012
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Andrews, Jesse.
6.0 Linear Feet 150 Items
Photojournalist and regional documentary photographer working primarily in Virginia and North Carolina.
Consists of 149 gelatin silver black-and-white prints dating from 1973 to 2012, the majority of which document rural life in the Piedmont plateau of Virginia and North Carolina. There are many portraits of farmers, their families, Latino workers, and other local people, and scenes from their homesteads and farms. Themes include farming, tobacco cultivation, and tobacco auctions; activities such as music-making, dancing, hunting, and working with hides and leather; the lives and struggles of American war veterans; and the status of regional economies and small businesses in rural Virginia in the late 20th century. Additional projects include a series of images taken by Andrews from an Amtrak train during a trip from New York City to Lynchburg, Virginia, and street scenes and portraits of individuals taken in New York City, Massachusetts, North Carolina, Tennessee, and California; there are also a few abstract images of plants and one of ice on a pond. An oral history recording of a veteran is also included in the collection. Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
Administrative Information
Online Items
Images from this collection have been digitized and are available in: Jesse Andrews Photographs - Duke Digital Collections.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research, but is restricted to educational, non-commercial use. Photographer retains all copyrights and must be contacted for any other use.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Jesse Pyrant Andrews photographs were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 2003, 2006, 2007, 2008, and 2011.
Biographical Note
Photojournalist and regional documentary photographer Jesse Pyrant Andrews (b. 1949) is based in southern Virginia, and has photographed the changing rural landscapes of Virginia and North Carolina and the lives of its inhabitants since 1975. His work includes photographs of buildings in small southeastern towns, landscapes from train windows, farms and rural farming communities. Many of his photographs document the effects of the industrialization of tobacco farming on communities that once depended on tobacco as their economic base. Andrews has also photographed Latino workers and has documented, with photographs and oral histories, the lives of disabled veterans. He studied at the New England School of Photography in Boston, Massachusetts, working primarily with photographers Olive Pierce and George Dewolfe. He shoots 35mm black-and-white film which he prints in his traditional wet darkroom.
Collection Overview
The Jesse Pyrant Andrews Photographs collection consists of 149 gelatin silver black-and-white prints dating from 1973 to 2012, the majority of which document rural life in the Piedmont plateau of Virginia and North Carolina. There is also one oral history associated with a print. There are many portraits of farmers, their families, Latino workers, and other local people, and scenes from their homesteads and farms. Themes include farming, tobacco cultivation, and tobacco auctions; activities such as music-making, dancing, hunting, tanning animal hides, and braiding leather; the lives and struggles of American war veterans; and the status of regional economies and small businesses in rural Virginia in the late 20th century. Photographs from the series documenting tobacco farming, 13-Month Crop, were selected for a 2002 exhibit of Andrew's work hosted by the Rubenstein Library at Duke University.
Two related bodies of documentary work whose images form part of the Virginia Photographs Series are the Disabled Veterans and the Carter-Wooding projects. The first examines the lives and struggles of American war veterans and includes a recorded oral history of a vet. The second documents the history of two families and their Virginia farm in Halifax County, which dates back to an original 18th-century land grant to the Carter family. Additional projects in the collection include a series of images taken by Andrews from an Amtrak train during a trip from New York City to Lynchburg, Virginia, and street scenes and portraits of individuals taken in New York City, Massachusetts, North Carolina, Tennessee, and California; there are also several abstract images of plants and one of ice on a pond.
In many cases the photographs are accompanied by captions written by the photographer commenting on the individuals, their life histories, and aspects of regional or local culture. Original identification numbers and titles assigned by the photographer were retained and a Rubenstein Library id added. Any titles in brackets were supplied by the archivist as additional description. The original code on the back of the prints has also been retained that indicates series, negative file, and negative number, i.e., POR-3-47-9, meaning the Portrait Series, notebook 3, page 47, negative 9
Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
Arranged in the following series: 13-Month Crop, 2000-2001; Bill Davis and Davis Family, 1976-2006; Portraits, 1992-2008; Train Project, 2011-2012; Virginia Photographs, 1976-2008 and undated; and Other Prints, 1973-2010.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Andrews, Jesse
Agriculture -- Virginia -- Pictorial works
Country life -- Virginia -- Pictorial works
Documentary photographers -- Virginia
Documentary photography -- Virginia -- Pittsylvania County
Farm life -- Virginia
Farms -- Virginia -- Pictorial works
Rural conditions -- Virginia
Tobacco farmers -- Virginia
Tobacco farmers -- Virginia -- Pittsylvania County -- Pictorial works
Tobacco industry -- Virginia -- Pittsylvania County
Train travel -- Pictorial works
Veterans -- United States -- Social conditions -- 20th century
Halifax County (Va.) -- Pictorial works
Pittsylvania County (Va.) -- Pictorial works
Virginia -- Pictorial works
Black-and-white photographs
Gelatin silver prints
Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University)
Related Material
Five Farms: Stories from American Farm Families photographs, 2008
Rubenstein Library, Duke University
Contents of Collection
- 13-Month Crop Series, 2000-2001, (37 prints)
  Consists of 37 black-and-white, 11x14 inch prints exhibited at Duke University's Perkins Library, August 7-December 14, 2002. Andrews spent a year photographing the people involved in cultivating tobacco on the Moore family farm in Pittsylvania County, Virginia, during one tobacco season, April 2000-April 2001. Includes images of family members as well as Hispanic laborers. Tobacco farming is such labor-intensive work that it is often called a "13-month crop." All titles and captions in this series were supplied by the photographer. Original print numbers have been retained. Arranged in original order as received.
  - Charles Moore and Terry Moore preparing land for planting, early spring 2000 (Box 1, Image RL10010_P_001)
    Orig. print number: JA_13MCA_1_34
  - Lillian Moore at the Moore homeplace, 2000 (Box 1, Image RL10010_P_002)
    Orig. print number: JA_13MCA_1_20
  - Terry and his daughter Christine during a break from seeding greenhouse trays, early spring 2001 (Box 1, Image RL10010_P_003)
    Orig. print number: JA_13MCA_5_33
  - Christine helping with the seeding of the greenhouse trays, early spring 2001 (Box 1, Image RL10010_P_004)
    Orig. print number: JA_13MCA_6_19
  - Roy Younger placing seeded trays in the greenhouse bed, early spring 2001 (Box 1, Image RL10010_P_005)
    Orig. print number: JA_13MCA_3_24A_25
  - Terry with a tray of seedlings ready for planting, spring 2000 (Box 1, Image RL10010_P_006)
    Orig. print number: JA_13MCA_3_18A_19
  - Loading the planter on the first day of planting, spring 2000 (Box 1, Image RL10010_P_007)
    Orig. print number: JA_13MCA_3_9
  - First day of planting, spring 2000 (Box 1, Image RL10010_P_008)
    Orig. print number: JA_13MCA_1_10
  - Planting, spring 2000 (Box 1, Image RL10010_P_009)
    Orig. print number: JA_13MCA_1_22A
  - Eduardo Pineda Arzata, who has worked at the Moore farm for twelve years, at the curing barns, summer 2000 (Box 1, Image RL10010_P_010)
    Orig. print number: JA_13MCA_4_2
  - Leonel Perez Gutierrez, who has worked at the Moore farm for four years, summer 2000 (Box 1, Image RL10010_P_011)
    Orig. print number: JA_13MCA_4_11
  - Maximo Perez Gutierrez, who has worked at the Moore farm for nine years, summer 2000 (Box 1, Image RL10010_P_012)
    Orig. print number: JA_13MCA_4_8
  - Eduardo Pineda Arzata cultivating by hand, spring 2000 (Box 1, Image RL10010_P_013)
    Orig. print number: JA_13MCA_5_24
  - Cam Moore, Terry's son, cultivating young tobacco, late spring 2000 (Box 1, Image RL10010_P_014)
    Orig. print number: JA_13MCA_5_29A_30
  - Terry in the final step of cultivation known as laying by, late spring 2000 (Box 1, Image RL10010_P_015)
    Orig. print number: JA_13MCA_6_32
  - Christine Moore aboard Moira and Renee, her mother, summer 2000 (Box 1, Image RL10010_P_016)
    Orig. print number: JA_13MCA_2_22
  - The Moore family gathered at the homeplace after Sunday dinner, summer 2000 (Box 1, Image RL10010_P_017)
    Orig. print number: JA_13MCA_6_5
  - Terry and workers, from left to right, Leonel, Eduardo and Maximo spraying to control tobacco stalk shoots called suckers, summer 2000 (Box 1, Image RL10010_P_018)
    Orig. print number: JA_13MCA_2_29A_30
  - Eduardo topping the flowered plants, summer 2000 (Box 1, Image RL10010_P_019)
    Orig. print number: JA_13MCA_6_24
  - Irrigating, summer 2000 (Box 1, Image RL10010_P_020)
    Orig. print number: JA_13MCA_2_33
  - Terry inspecting for suckers, summer 2000 (Box 2, Image RL10010_P_021)
    Orig. print number: JA_13MCA_1_6
  - Pulling or harvesting the top leaves near the season's end, summer 2000 (Box 2, Image RL10010_P_022)
    Orig. print number: JA_13MCA_2_9A_10
  - Charles Moore and workers with the final trailer of tobacco of the season, late summer 2000 (Box 2, Image RL10010_P_023)
    Orig. print number: JA_13MCA_5_36
  - Early morning, Terry sweeping out an empty barn, summer 2000 (Box 2, Image RL10010_P_024)
    Orig. print number: JA_13MCA_3_22
  - Betty Starlin, Terry, and Eduardo Pineda taking a break from barning, summer 2000 (Box 2, Image RL10010_P_025)
    Orig. print number: JA_13MCA_1_31
  - Pro-tobacco poster at Holland's Warehouse, late summer 2000 (Box 2, Image RL10010_P_026)
    Orig. print number: JA_13MCA_6_26
  - Terry with cousins Caleb and George Moore at their farm, summer 2000 (Box 2, Image RL10010_P_027)
    Orig. print number: JA_13MCA_5_6
  - Leonel Perez baling cured tobacco early morning, summer 2000 (Box 2, Image RL10010_P_028)
    Orig. print number: JA_13MCA_6_22
  - Betty and Eduardo barning newly pulled leaves, summer 2000 (Box 2, Image RL10010_P_029)
    Orig. print number: JA_13MCA_2_32
  - Terry and Leonel sheeting cured leaves from the barns, summer 2000 (Box 2, Image RL10010_P_030)
    Orig. print number: JA_13MCA_3_28
  - Sheeting tobacco at Caleb and George's farm, summer 2000 (Box 2, Image RL10010_P_031)
    Orig. print number: JA_13MCA_1_30
  - Eduardo, Leonel, and Maximo pushing an 850 pound bale of tobacco onto the loader in preparation for market, summer 2000 (Box 2, Image RL10010_P_032)
    Orig. print number: JA_13MCA_2_19
  - Terry and Charles at Holland's Warehouse on the first day of the market, Danville, Va., summer 2000 (Box 2, Image RL10010_P_033)
    Orig. print number: JA_13MCA_1_36
  - Terry with Dan and Danny Robertson, Owners of Holland's Warehouse, Danville, Va., summer 2000 (Box 2, Image RL10010_P_034)
    Orig. print number: JA_13MCA_5_30
  - A tobacco auction in progress, Hollan's Warehouse, Danville, Va., late summer 2000 (Box 2, Image RL10010_P_035)
    Orig. print number: JA_13MCA_5_20
  - Terry receiving his check for tobacco sales, Holland's Warehouse, Danville, Va., late summer 2000 (Box 2, Image RL10010_P_036)
    Orig. print number: JA_13MCA_6_25
  - Terry sows wheat as a cover crop, fall 2000 (Box 2, Image RL10010_P_037)
    Orig. print number: JA_13MCA_3_36
- Bill Davis and Davis Family Series, 1976-2006, (18 prints)
  Contains 18 11x14 inch black-and-white gelatin silver prints, the majority of which feature Bill Davis and the Davis family, a rural family from the Piedmont plateau region of Pittsylvania County, south-central Virginia. Titles and captions supplied by the photographer; information in brackets supplied by library staff; original print numbers have been retained. Organized in original order as received.
  - William Arastus Davis (Bill), 1988 (Box 2, Image RL10010_P_038)
    Orig. print number: JA_POR_4x5_1
  - Bill Davis braiding a belt from deer hide, 1988 (Box 2, Image RL10010_P_039)
    Orig. print number: JA_POR_88_20
    Bill learned to braid leather when he was a child. His father did not want him to learn that craft so he would take the strands of leather under the covers of his bed at night and practice braiding simply by feel. He could do any sort of braid from the most simple to making what he called a rosette, a round knot woven from 16 strands of leather, seemingly with no beginning or end.
  - Bill Davis playing a chromatic harmonica, 1988 (Box 2, Image RL10010_P_040)
    Orig. print number: JA_POR_45_26A
    The chair he is sitting in was made by his grandfather, Simeon Benton Davis.
  - Bill Davis with his younger sister, Nancy Paige Davis, 1990 (Box 2, Image RL10010_P_041)
    Orig. print number: JA_POR_43_16A
    Bill was much older than Nancy. When she turned 18, she wanted to attend the nursing school at the University of Virginia, but their father refused to pay for her to go. Bill eventually saved enough money to send her and she graduated in 1941. She never returned to the farm except to visit and lived in Richmond until her death in 2005. This image was made during her last visit to see Bill. She always referred to him as her angel and thus she was making a halo for him.
  - Orbrey Nathaniel Davis (Nat), 1979 (Box 2, Image RL10010_P_042)
    Orig. print number: JA_POR_88_38
    Nat had been telling me about one of his first girlfriends. He was sad because he thought no one would ever care for him again.
  - Bill and Nat Davis playing music on their front porch, 1978 (Box 2, Image RL10010_P_043)
    Orig. print number: JA_POR_42_27
    They knew hundreds of old time tunes as well as hymns and ballads.
  - Bill Davis grave, November 2006 (Box 2, Image RL10010_P_044)
    Orig. print number: JA_LAL_12_XX
  - The Davis family cemetery, 2006 (Box 2, Image RL10010_P_045)
  - All that is left of what Nat Davis referred to as the big woods, undated (Box 2, Image RL10010_P_046)
    Orig. print number: JA_LAL_14_XX
    This is where Hat and Bill hunted and trapped their entire lives. Bill used to say that the mound in the background was an Indian burial place.
  - Site of the Davis family spring, November 2006 (Box 2, Image RL10010_P_047)
    This spring was where they got their water for nearly 100 years. It is now a mosquito breeding ground.
  - Site of the Davis family homeplace, November 2006 (Box 3, Image RL10010_P_048)
    Orig. print number: JA_LAL_13_XX
  - William Arastus Davis (Bill Davis), 1900_1991, on the Davis Farm near Chatham, Va., 1976 (Box 3, Image RL10010_P_049)
    Orig. print number: JA_POR_84_43
    Bill was a friend of my grandmother. When I was a child, she would take me with her to visit the Davis farm. I knew the Davises very well. They are all dead now, their farm sold and is now a high-end housing development. The Davis family was a real link to the past. They never got accustomed to the Twentieth Century.
  - Bill Davis, November, 1989 (Box 3, Image RL10010_P_050)
    Orig. print number: JA_POR_42_24
    Bill had gotten out his wool army uniform for cold weather.
  - Bill Davis' burial, August, 1991 (Box 3, Image RL10010_P_051)
    Orig. print number: JA_POR_51_12A
    Pictured are (from left) Calvin Daniel, Ricky Adkins, and Dennis Daniel. Calvin Daniel inherited the Davis farm. These men dug Bill's grave. They and I were the only people at the burial. Bill asked me to make this last image of him at the family cemetery.
  - Orbrey Nathaniel Davis (Nat Davis), 1898_1987, at Davis farm, October, 1978 (Box 3, Image RL10010_P_052)
    Orig. print number: JA_POR_88_39
    This is Bill Davis' brother.
  - Nat Davis skinning foxes, November, 1984 (Box 3, Image RL10010_P_053)
    Orig. print number: JA_POR_56_8ND
    This was Nat's primary source of income. Occasionally he would trap a mink. Nat was also an avid turkey hunter.
  - Bill Davis on his birthday, May 21, 1989 (Box 3, Image RL10010_P_054)
    Orig. print number: JA_LAL_80_15
  - Bill Davis fleshing out a deer hide, Chatham, Va., 1982 (Box 3, Image RL10010_P_055)
    Orig. print number: JA_POR_45_30
    Bill would tan fresh deer hides to use in his leather work. He made a device which would split a hide into evenly sized strips for braiding. He made belts, sashes, hat bands, watch fobs, key holders, and guitar straps. He also did harness repairs and remade worn out shoes. But the first step in this process was to pick all the flesh off the hide. If left, the bits of flesh would attract insects to eat the hide and leave uncured spots on the finished hide.
- Portraits Series, 1992-2008, (12 prints)
  Twelve black-and-white portraits of individuals from Virginia and North Carolina, including children, adults with children, and mothers with adult sons. Original print numbers and titles assigned by the photographer are retained. Arranged in original order as received.
  - Mark Aaron, Esmont, Va., 2003 (Box 3, Image RL10010_P_132)
    Orig. print number: JA_LAL_65_8
  - Mark Aaron, Callands, Va., 2001 (Box 3, Image RL10010_P_133)
    Orig. print number: JA_LAL_147_9
  - Stewart Werner and his son Stewart Werner Jr., Halifax, Va., 2007 (Box 3, Image RL10010_P_134)
    Orig. print number: JA_POR_116_6
  - Rud Shupik, Callands, Va., 2002 (Box 3, Image RL10010_P_135)
    Orig. print number: JA_POR_57_14
  - Rud Shupik, Riceville, Va., 2001 (Box 3, Image RL10010_P_136)
    Orig. print number: JA_POR_2_15
  - Moira Riser, Pelham, N.C., 2003 (Box 3, Image RL10010_P_137)
    Orig. print number: JA_POR_14-3
  - John Riser, Pelham, N.C., 2003 (Box 3, Image RL10010_P_138)
    Orig. print number: JA_POR_14_7
  - Rachael Martin, Halifax, Va., 2008 (Box 3, Image RL10010_P_139)
    Orig. print number: JA_POR_123_8
  - Giles Motley, Pittsylvania County, Va., 1998 (Box 3, Image RL10010_P_140)
    Orig. print number: JA_POR_41_14
  - Watermelon vendor, Tightsqueeze, Va., 1992 (Box 3, Image RL10010_P_141)
    Orig. print number: JA_POR_86_27
  - Richard Stoner and his mother, Beatrice Stoner, 2004 (Box 3, Image RL10010_P_142)
    Orig. print number: JA_POR_106_12
  - Jerry Smith and his mother, Norma Smith, 2003 (Box 3, Image RL10010_P_143)
    Orig. print number: JA_4x5_PORTRAITS_9
- View from Amtrak Northeast Regional, Train #147, Train Project Series, 2010, (31 prints)
  These 31 11x14 inch images were taken by Jesse Andrews on November 19, 2010 using traditional black-and-white film during a train trip from New York City to Lynchburg, Virginia. Images were chiefly taken from the windows of the moving train and capture overpasses, traffic, graffiti, residential neighborhoods, train stations, and other urban landscapes; a few shots focus on train passengers and there is one of a railroad worker on the tracks.
  Descriptive titles in brackets supplied by library staff. All prints were developed in 2011 and 2012. Original print numbers assigned by the photographer are retained.
  - [Tracks underneath power lines], 2010 Nov. 19 (Box 3, Image RL10010_P_056)
    Orig. print number: JA_LAL_110_3A_4
  - [Boat on large river, bridge in distance], 2010 Nov. 19 (Box 3, Image RL10010_P_057)
    Orig. print number: JA_LAL_110_33
  - [Graffiti reading "Depression"], 2010 Nov. 19 (Box 3, Image RL10010_P_058)
    Orig. print number: JA_LAL_108_24
  - [Woman sleeping in window seat on train], 2010 Nov. 19 (Box 3, Image RL10010_P_059)
    Orig. print number: JA_LAL_111_1A
  - [Graffiti beneath highway pillars], 2010 Nov. 19 (Box 3, Image RL10010_P_060)
    Orig. print number: JA_LAL_109_12A
  - [Houses and street with white car], 2010 Nov. 19 (Box 3, Image RL10010_P_061)
    Orig. print number: JA_LAL_110_21_A
  - [Cars on highway and graffiti], 2010 Nov. 19 (Box 3, Image RL10010_P_062)
    Orig. print number: JA_LAL_109_30A
  - [Large graffiti on factory wall], 2010 Nov. 19 (Box 3, Image RL10010_P_063)
    Orig. print number: JA_LAL_108_17
  - [Large river and cars on highway], 2010 Nov. 19 (Box 3, Image RL10010_P_064)
    Orig. print number: JA_LAL_108_37
  - [Bare trees and field beyond], 2010 Nov. 19 (Box 3, Image RL10010_P_065)
    Orig. print number: JA_LAL_111_6
  - [Tall grasses and weeds underneath highway from moving train], 2010 Nov. 19 (Box 3, Image RL10010_P_066)
    Orig. print number: JA_LAL_111_7
  - [Cemetery and trees from moving train], 2010 Nov. 19 (Box 3, Image RL10010_P_067)
    Orig. print number: JA_LAL_111_30A
  - [River and trees next to tracks], 2010 Nov. 19 (Box 3, Image RL10010_P_068)
    Orig. print number: JA_LAL_111_7A_8
  - [Tracks and white structure with graffiti beneath overpass], 2010 Nov. 19 (Box 3, Image RL10010_P_069)
    Orig. print number: JA_LAL_111_25A_26
  - [Abandoned building with many glass windows], 2010 Nov. 19 (Box 3, Image RL10010_P_070)
    Orig. print number: JA_LAL_108_15
  - ["Sale Lease" sign behind wire], 2010 Nov. 19 (Box 4, Image RL10010_P_071)
    Orig. print number: JA_LAL_109_6A
  - [Fence and clouds framed by interior train window], 2010 Nov. 19 (Box 4, Image RL10010_P_072)
    Orig. print number: JA_LAL_111_36
  - [Narrow tree-lined canal and buildings beyond, from overpass], 2010 Nov. 19 (Box 4, Image RL10010_P_073)
    Orig. print number: JA_LAL_108_27
  - [White wall with graffiti, factories in distance], 2010 Nov. 19 (Box 4, Image RL10010_P_074)
    Orig. print number: JA_LAL_108_30
  - [Street with parked cars and church], 2010 Nov. 19 (Box 4, Image RL10010_P_075)
    Orig. print number: JA_LAL_108_19
  - [Crane and houses behind sheet metal fence with graffiti], 2010 Nov. 19 (Box 4, Image RL10010_P_076)
    Orig. print number: JA_LAL_108_25
  - [Globe Dye Works sign on factory roof behind trees], 2010 Nov. 19 (Box 4, Image RL10010_P_077)
  - [Line of attached houses, tracks in foreground], 2010 Nov. 19 (Box 4, Image RL10010_P_078)
    Orig. print number: JA_LAL_111_13A
  - [Graffiti on wall, trees and power lines beyond], 2010 Nov. 19 (Box 4, Image RL10010_P_079)
    Orig. print number: JA_LAL_108_16
  - [Stone prison-like structure with corner tower, barbed wire fence], 2010 Nov. 19 (Box 4, Image RL10010_P_080)
    Orig. print number: JA_LAL_108_14
  - [Highway ramp and avenue running through town], 2010 Nov. 19 (Box 4, Image RL10010_P_081)
    Orig. print number: JA_LAL_108_20
  - [Overhead view of tree-lined tracks], 2010 Nov. 19 (Box 4, Image RL10010_P_082)